kimi wa ima namida nagashita
I can see the tears in your eyes,
nakijakuru kodomo no you ni
you're just like a crying child
tatoe asu ga mienaku natte mo mamoru yo
I'll keep you safe even though I don't know what tomorrow will bring
natsu no sora miagete niranda
I'll stare up to the summer sky
tsuyogatte bakari de namida wa misenai
You act tough, and never show any tears
hontou wa kowai kuseni
But I know you're scared
taisetsu na mono wo ushinawa nu you ni
You keep running so you don't lose what's important
hisshi de hashirinukete kita
We've always survived through the long night
itsu datte nagai yoru wo futari de norikoeta
I'll always be by your side
kono mama issho ni iru kara
So you don't need to act tough
tsuyogatte naide ii nda yo
kimi wa ima namida nagashita
I can see the tears in your eyes,
nakijakuru kodomo no you ni
you're just like a crying child
tatoe asu ga mienaku natte mo susumu yo
We'll keep moving forward
even though we don't know what tomorrow will bring
natsu no sora miagete sakenda
I'll scream up to the summer sky
natsu no sora miagete niranda
I'll stare up to the summer sky
Lost Bonds
（ナルト）俺たち
第七班でやってきたことは→
Don't all those things we did
together in Squad 7
全部　何の意味もなかったのかよ？
mean anything to you?!
（サスケ）いや　無意味じゃない。
No... It wasn't meaningless.
俺にとってお前は　最も→
To me, you became...
親しい友になった。
my closest friend.
友になった？　だったら何で？
I became your friend?
だからこそだ。
Then why?
That's precisely why.
だからこそ→
お前には殺す価値がある。
That's precisely why...
you're worth killing.
（ヤマト）気がついたか？
You're finally awake?
夢…。
A dream?
俺ってば…。
気絶したんだよ。
Where am I?
心配かけてホント…。
You lost consciousness.
You really had us worried.
カカシ先生とサイは？
Where are Kakashi Sensei and Sai?
そうか。
I see.
何でだ？
Why?
何で　こうなっちまう？
Why did it turn out like this?
ナルト　もう少し休んだほうがいい。
Naruto...
You should rest a bit longer.
さあ。
Come on.
《サスケ　お前は…》
Sasuke... you're...
((知ってるか？
うちは一族って
みんな殺されたらしいぜ。
Did you hear?
Everyone in the Uchiha Clan got killed.
ああ　知ってる知ってる。
父ちゃんが言ってた。
Yeah, I know.
I heard my dad talking about it.
(生き残ったの　アイツだけらしいぜ))
He's the only one who survived.
《あのとき俺は　嬉しかった。
I was sorta glad back then.
同じ孤独なヤツがいることが…》
I wasn't the only one
who was alone anymore.
《だけどサスケは
何をやっても　うまくできた》
But Sasuke was good
at everything he did.
((イルカ：おお　やるなサスケ。
（イノ）さすがサスケ君！
（サクラ）かっこいい！
Good job, Sasuke!
Just what I'd expect from Sasuke!
ヘッ　かっこつけやがって。
He's so cool!
He's showing off!
I can do that too!
(あんなの
俺にだって　できるってばよ))
《俺とは違ってた》
He was so different from me.
((行け！))
Go!
《だから勝手に　ライバルに決めた。
That's why I picked him
to be my rival,
アイツみたいになりたかったから》
because I wanted to
become like him.
((でや～！))
《同じ七班になっても→
Even though we were both on Squad 7,
サスケは　俺より一歩前にいた》
Sasuke was always
one step ahead of me.
《必死に修業したのは→
The reason why I trained so hard
was because
少しでも
追いつきたかったからだった》
I wanted to catch up to him,
even just a little.
俺は強いのか？
"Am I strong?"
All I want is the answer to that.
ただその答えがほしい。
ここで　強いヤツと
戦いたかっただけだ。
I just wanted to fight the strong ones.
そして　ソイツらは　ここにいる。
And they are all right here.
(ナルト　俺はお前とも戦いたい))
Naruto... I want to fight you too.
《本当に嬉しかった。
I was really happy.
サスケが　俺を認めてくれた
初めての言葉》
It was the first time Sasuke
acknowledged me as an equal.
((カカシ：そうだな　まずは
自己紹介してもらおう))
First off, let's have you guys
introduce yourselves.
《だけど　アイツは…》
名は　うちはサスケ。
But he...
My name's Sasuke Uchiha.
嫌いなものなら　たくさんあるが
好きなものは別にない。
I have lots of dislikes,
but no likes in particular.
それから　夢なんて言葉で
終わらす気はないが→
And I don't feel like summing up
my ambition as just a dream,
野望はある。
but I do have an ambition.
一族の復興と
ある男を必ず殺すことだ。
The ambition to restore my clan and
to kill a certain man
without fail!
（イタチ）久しぶりだな　サスケ。
It's been a long time... Sasuke.
うちはイタチ。
えっ！？
Itachi Uchiha...
アンタを殺す！
I will kill you!
《コイツが　サスケが言っていた
殺したい男》
This is the guy
Sasuke talked about,
the man he wants to kill?
アンタの言ったとおり
アンタを恨み　憎み→
It's just as you said...
I've hated you...
and resented you.
そして　アンタを殺すためだけに
俺は…。
For the singular purpose
of killing you, I...
俺は…。
I...
(生きてきた！))
《お前は
復讐に生きることを決めた》
have lived my life!
You decided to live for revenge.
((サイ：確かに　僕の極秘任務の命は
サスケ君の暗殺だった。
My classified mission was indeed
the assassination of Sasuke.
けど　命令はもういい。
But I've had enough of orders.
今は自分の考えで動きたい。
I now want to act
on my own beliefs.
ナルト君が
思い出させてくれそうなんだ。
I think Naruto will get me
to remember...
僕の昔の気持を。
my past emotions.
僕は　キミのことを
よく知らないけど→
I don't know you very well.
ナルト君やサクラさんが
ここまで必死に　キミを追うのには→
But there must be
some kind of reason
何か　わけがある。
Naruto and Sakura have pursued
you so desperately.
キミとのつながりを切るまいと→
They don't want to sever
their bonds with you.
つなぎとめておこうと
必死になってる。
They're giving it their all
to secure those bonds.
僕には　まだ
はっきりとは　わからない。
I still don't understand it
all that clearly.
けど　サスケ君
キミには　わかってるはずだ。
But Sasuke, you should understand.
ああ　わかってた。
Yeah, I did understand.
だから　断ち切った。
That's why I severed the bonds.
I have a different bond.
俺には　別のつながりがある。
(兄との憎しみっていう
つながりがな))
A bond of hatred with
my older brother.
《俺とサスケのつながりは…》
What about the bond
between Sasuke and me?
((さっさとこい！
その前に　額あてしろ。
Hurry up!
Before that, put your headband on.
I'll wait.
待ってやる。
いらねえよ　そんなもんは。
I don't need that thing.
いいから　しろ！
お前は　俺の額に→
Just do it!
You won't even be able to put
a scratch on my forehead!
傷一つ　つけることすら
できやしない。
違う　これは木ノ葉の忍として→
That's not it!
I'm saying this is a testament
対等に戦う証だって
言ってんだよ。
to fighting on equal terms
as Leaf Ninja.
そういうのが
図にのってるっていうんだ！
And I'm saying you're acting
high and mighty!
テメエと俺が
対等だと思ってんのか？
Do you really think that we're equals?!
ああ　思ってる。
俺は　一度も→
Yeah, I do!
お前に劣ってるとは
思ったことはねえよ。
I've never once thought that
I was inferior to you!
目障りなんだよ！
それは　お前が→
You're an embarrassment!
弱いままだからだろうが。
サスケちゃんよ。
That's because you're still weak,
Little Sasuke!
ナルト！
サスケ！
Naruto!
やめて　２人とも。
Sasuke!
Stop it, both of you.
やめてよ！
Stop it!
２人とも　やめて！
Stop it, both of you!
クソ！
止め切れねえ。
Damn!
I can't stop completely!
うわぁ！
（君麻呂）大蛇丸様は
すでに不死の術を手にしている。
Lord Orochimaru has already
acquired the Immortality Jutsu.
不死といっても　肉体がそのまま
保ち続けるわけではない。
"Immortal" doesn't mean that
his flesh can maintain itself forever.
体が朽ちる前に
強く新しい肉体を→
Before his body decays,
魂の器にする。
a strong, new body must be made
into a vessel for his soul.
それが…　それが
サスケだってのか！？
That's...
Are you saying that's Sasuke?!
ああ　そうだ。
Yes... That's right.
そんなこと　俺がさせるか！？
I won't let that happen!
《サスケが里を捨てたとき→
When Sasuke abandoned the village,
俺は　アイツを連れ戻せると
思っていた。　だけど…》
I really believed
I could bring him back.
But...
((いい加減に目が覚めたかよ！
Have you snapped out of it yet?
親も兄弟もいねえ　テメエに
俺の何がわかるってんだよ！
You have no siblings or parents.
How could you understand
anything about me?!
初めから１人きりだった　テメエに
俺の何がわかるってんだ！
You've been on your own
since the beginning!
What makes you think
you know anything about me?
つながりがあるからこそ
苦しいんだ。
Having that bond is
what makes it painful!
それを失うことが　どんなもんか→
And how could you know
(お前なんかに
わかってたまるか！))
what it feels like
to lose that bond?!
《結局　俺は　サスケのことを
何もわかっちゃいなかった。
In the end,
I didn't understand Sasuke at all.
わかったつもりで
いただけだった》
I just thought I knew him.
((何でだ？
何で　そこまでして俺に。
Why?
Why would you go
so far for me?
俺にとっちゃ
やっとできた　つながりなんだ。
Because this is the first bond
that I've ever had!
だから俺は
お前を止めるんだってばよ！
That's why I'm gonna stop you.
認めてやるよ　お前は強い。
I admit it, you're strong.
なぜなら　お前も俺と同じ
孤独の痛みを知る者だ。
It's because you know the pain
that solitude brings,
just as I do.
そして　その痛みが人を強くする。
And it's that pain that
makes people stronger.
だからこそ
このつながりを断つことで→
And for that very reason,
if I break that bond,
俺は　更なる強さを手に入れる。
I'll be able to achieve
even greater strength.
知ってるか？　ここは
終末の谷と呼ばれる国境だ。
Did you know that this place
is called the Final Valley?
ちょうどいい舞台じゃねえか
なあ　ナルト。
Don't you think this is
a perfect stage for us, Naruto?
You...
(じゃあ　そろそろしまいにしようぜ
この戦いを))
So let's bring this fight
to a close soon!
気分はどう？
おかゆを作ってもらったよ。
How are you feeling?
これを食べて
体力を回復するんだ。
I had them make some porridge.
Eat it and restore your strength.
今　サスケの夢を見てた。
I... was dreaming about Sasuke.
お前は　僕と一緒に里へ帰る。
You're going back to
the village with me.
カカシ先輩の命令だよ。
They're Kakashi's orders.
悪いけど　サスケのことは
カカシ先輩に任せるんだ。　いいね？
I'm sorry, but you just have to
let Kakashi handle Sasuke.
Got it?
わかってる。
Fine.
もう少し休んだら
里に戻るってばよ。
Let me rest some more,
then we can head back to the village.
体調を戻すためにも
少しは食べたほうがいい。
You should eat a little
to restore your strength.
食欲なんて　ねえってばよ。
I don't have an appetite.
((サスケは　俺とのつながりを
断ち切って→
Sasuke said he was going to sever
his bond with me
強くなるって言ってた。
and become stronger.
お前なんかに
俺の気持はわからないって。
He said I could never
understand his feelings.
エロ仙人と　大蛇丸も
昔　友達だったんだろ？
You were friends with Orochimaru
long ago, right, Pervy Sage?
どうして　大蛇丸は里を抜けて→
Why did Orochimaru desert the village
木ノ葉くずしなんか
したんだってばよ？
and decide to destroy
the Hidden Leaf?
（自来也）大蛇丸が
おかしくなってきたのは→
Orochimaru changed after
his parents were killed.
両親を殺されてからだ。
それからは
禁術にとりつかれていった。
He became obsessed
with Forbidden Jutsu.
両親に会いたかったのか。
Maybe he longed to see his parents,
それとも　両親を死に追いやった
木ノ葉への復讐か。
or he sought revenge
on the Leaf Village,
who he held responsible
for their deaths.
わしは　親を殺されては
おらんからのう。
My parents weren't killed.
わしも　お前と同じだ。
So like you, I was accused of
not being able to understand.
アイツに何もわかってないと
一喝されてのう。
そのとおり　アイツのことを→
Perhaps he was right,
何も　わかって
やれんかったのかもしれん。
I didn't understand
a thing about him.
だがのう　こんなわしでも
この忍の世に→
However...
even I can see there's too much
hate in our Ninja World.
憎しみが
はびこっているのはわかる。
憎しみ？
その憎しみをどうにかしたいとは
思っとるんだが。
Hate?
And I've wanted to do
something about this hatred,
どうしたらいいのか
わしにも　まだわからん。
but I'm not sure what
must be done.
だが　いつかは。
But I have faith that
人が本当の意味で
理解しあえる時代が来ると→
there will come a time
(わしは信じとる))
when people can truly
understand one another.
《俺にとって　エロ仙人は
かけがえのない家族だった》
To me, Pervy Sage was irreplaceable.
He was family.
《だから…》
That's why...
((フカサク：自来也ちゃんが戦死した。
Jiraiya-boy has died in battle.
(はあ？))
《エロ仙人が死んだって
聞いたとき→
When I heard that Pervy Sage died,
サスケの言っていた→
絆を失うことの
つらさってやつが→
I understood what Sasuke was
talking about for the very first time.
初めてわかった》
About the pain of losing a bond.
ナルト　そろそろ行くよ。
Naruto, let's go soon.
Are you still not ready?
まだか？
今は　外に出る気にならねぇんだ。
I don't feel like going outside yet.
もうちょっと待ってよ。
Can you wait a bit longer?
《よし！　まだ俺が影分身だって
気づかれてねえってばよ》
All right. He still hasn't caught on
that I'm a Shadow Clone.
((少しは　痛みを理解できたか？
Have you come to understand
a little of what pain is?
同じ痛みを知らなければ
他人を本当には理解できない。
Unless you know the same pain,
you cannot truly know another.
そして　理解をしたところで
わかりあえるわけでもない。
And even if you get to know others,
there can be no understanding.
それが　道理だ。
That is the truth.
お前が　サスケを追いかけても
ムダなようにな。
Just like how it's useless
to chase after Sasuke.
（カブト）人は変わる。
サスケ君は
もう昔のサスケ君じゃないんだよ。
People change...
Sasuke isn't the old Sasuke anymore.
（マダラ）サスケ自身が
そう選択したのさ。
Sasuke chose this himself.
サスケのことは　あきらめるんだのう。
You must forget about Sasuke.
忍として生きるなら
もっと賢くなれ。
If you are a ninja, become wiser.
バカのままじゃ　この世界
生きづらいのが現実だ。
Fools cannot survive in our world.
That is the reality.
賢いってのが
そういうことなら→
If being smart means
what you say,
(俺は　一生　バカでいい！))
I'll remain a fool for
the rest of my life.
《エロ仙人…　やっぱ俺は
大バカだってばよ！》
Pervy Sage, I'm a big fool after all.
カカシ先生のチャクラ！
こっちか！
Kakashi Sensei's chakra...
《サクラちゃん！　ムチャすんなよ！》
This way!
Sakura, don't do anything reckless.
((サイ：ここからは
僕の想像ですが→
This is just an assumption
on my part.
恐らく　サクラは…。
But I believe Sakura...
(１人で　サスケを殺すつもりだな))
She intends to kill Sasuke herself.
((サスケは　うちはの憎しみを
すべて背負い→
Sasuke has shouldered
the entire burden of the Uchiha's hatred
その憎しみの呪いを
世界へぶつけるつもりだ。
and intends to strike
the world with that curse.
最も強い武器であり
友であり力である憎しみ。
It is the most powerful weapon.
It's his friend and source of power,
this thing called hatred.
(それがサスケの忍道だ))
And it is Sasuke's Ninja Way!
((知ってるか？　ナルト。
Did you know, Naruto?
一流の忍同士なら
拳を一度交えただけで→
When two shinobi are of
a high enough level,
they are able to read
each other's thoughts,
互いの心の内が読めちまう。
simply by an exchange of fists.
口には出さなくてもだ。
Without ever uttering
a single word.
お前は甘いな　ナルト。
You're naïve, Naruto.
どうだ　お前には
本当の心の内が読めたか？
Tell me, could you read...
(この俺の))
my true feelings?
《サスケ　今なら→
Sasuke... Right now...
絆を失った　お前の気持
わかるってばよ》
I understand how you feel as
someone who has lost a bond.
((イタチ：さっき　お前は
サスケを兄弟のようだと言ったな。
You said earlier you consider
Sasuke to be like a brother.
ならば　もし　そのサスケが
木ノ葉を襲ってきたら→
What if Sasuke were to attack
the Leaf Village?
どうすると聞いているんだ。
What would you do then?
何だ？　なんでサスケが…
そんなことするわけねえだろ！
What? Why would Sasuke...?
There's no way he'd do
something like that!
サスケは　まだ純粋だ。
Sasuke is still naïve.
He can easily be dyed any color.
簡単に何色にでも染まる。
そうなった場合
お前はヤツを止められるのか？
Would you be able to stop him?
サスケを殺してでも。
Even if you had to kill Sasuke?
サスケと木ノ葉を
天秤にかけられるのか？
Could you weigh Sasuke
against the Leaf Village
木ノ葉は守る！
on a set of scales?
そんでもってサスケも
殺さず止める！
I would defend the Leaf Village!
But I would also stop Sasuke
without killing him!
子供だな。
お前の話は絵空事ばかりだ。
You're such a child.
What you speak of are
all fantasies.
(忍は時に厳しい選択を
迫られることだってある))
A ninja must sometimes
make very harsh decisions.
((雷影：暁は国際指名手配となる。
The Akatsuki will be branded
as wanted fugitives.
そうなれば　わしだけではない。
世界がサスケを狙う。
Then, not only I,
but the whole world will
hunt Sasuke down.
犯罪者のために頭を下げ
仲間の安全のために慈悲を請う。
Yet you bow your head
for this criminal
and plead for mercy for your friend.
(忍の世界で
それは友情とは言わん))
In the ninja world,
that is not friendship!
((我愛羅：影の名を
背負う覚悟を決めたなら→
If you are prepared to bear
the burden of being a Kage,
(サスケの友として　お前が本当に
やるべきことをやれ))
then do what is right
as Sasuke's friend.
《何をすべきかなんて
俺にもわからねえ。　だけど…》
I don't know what
the right thing to do is.
((木ノ葉のガキ　お前が何をすべきか
もっと考えろ。
However...
Boy from the Hidden Leaf,
think hard on what you must do!
(バカのまま　やり通せるほど
忍の世界は甘くない！))
The ninja world does not indulge fools!
((俺は　お前を友だと思っている。
I consider you my friend.
かつての俺にとって
友とは　ただの言葉。
In the past, "friend" was
merely a word to me.
それ以上でも
それ以下でもなかった。
Nothing more, nothing less.
だがお前と会って気づかされた。
But after meeting you,
you made me realize
大切なのは　その言葉の意味だと。
that the meaning of that word
is what's important.
その意味するところが何なのか。
What does it mean?
お前はサスケのために
何をしてやれるのか。
What can you do for Sasuke?
Think hard about that.
(よく考えろ))
《サスケ　お前に会えば…。
Sasuke...
If I see you...
会えば　答えがわかる気がする》
If we meet, I think
I'll know the answer.
te ashi tsunagareteru yo i'm like marionetto
My hands and feet are tied up, I'm Like a marionette
sonna no arienee yo ittai dounatteru yo
This is nonsense, What's going on?
tell me tell me who's the ruler? kiyasuku sawaruna
(Tell Me Tell Me) Who's the Ruler?
Don't put your hands on me
kikitakuneeyo mou kiben wa
I don't want to hear your false arguments anymore
kokkara sakiwa ore ga kimen da!
I'm in charge of my own life from now on
mienai kusari wo tachikire
Break the invisible chains
genkai sure sure dashikire
Test your limits
jibun de kachi toranakya
If you don't win it for yourself
darekano te ni watacchauze
Someone else will take it
stand up! saa mina reach out for liberty
Stand Up!! C'mon everybody Reach Out For Liberty
ima ga ugokidasu toki da
It's time to make a move
wake up! saa mina step up shite sakebe
Wake Up!! C'mon everybody Step Up and shout
oh yes we are the dreamer
run for your freedom
saki datsu mono nante nakutatte
Even though you don't have a reason
run for your freedom
yume no tobira kettobashite
Kick the door to your dream
so you better stand up!! saa mina reach out for liberty
(so you better) Stand Up!!
C'mon everybody Reach Out For Liberty
ima ga ugokidasu toki da
It's time to make a move
wake up! saa mina step up shite sakebe
Wake Up!! C'mon everybody Step Up and shout
oh yes we are the dreamer
run for your freedom
saki datsumono nante nakutatte
Even though you don't have a reason
run for your freedom
yume no tobira ketto bashite
Kick the door to your dream
fight for your freedom
（くもじい）
もしもし　そこのあなた。
Next Episode
たまには　空から日本を
眺めてみるというのは→
Sakura, you don't have to shoulder that burden yourself.
どうじゃろう？
今回は　瀬戸内海の島々を繋ぐ
しまなみ海道じゃ。
It was my cowardice that split all of you up.
I must have been trying to convince myself
（くもみ）うわぁ　大きな橋。
that it could be like the old days again.
海の交差点
瀬戸内海の船たちを眺めながら→
魅惑の島々を探検じゃ。
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "The Burden"
島がたくさん！
The Burden
I'm sorry I was such a careless teacher.